A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Population Program, Project Specialist in Communications, Office Files of William O. Sweeney FA571
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Population Program, Project Specialist in Communications, Office Files of William O. Sweeney
1968-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA571
1.6 Cubic Feet
The Office Files of William O. Sweeney document his work as a project specialist in population communications for the Foundation from 1969 to 1981. The collection is organized into two series: Project Files (1970-1980), and Reports and Writings (1968-1977). Mr. Sweeney's Project Files detail his work on the Foundation's Population Communications Project. The Reports and Writings focus on population communications. The files hold research reports, evaluations, conference papers and other writings authored by Mr. Sweeney The earliest Foundation grants for population research and family planning occurred under the aegis of the Divisions of International Affairs or Overseas Development. The Population Program was officially established in 1963, and became part of the International Division in 1966. Following a Foundation-wide reorganization in 1981, the Population program became an independent program area. In 1992 the Population Program was subsumed into Reproductive Health and Population. Following the Foundation-wide reorganization in 1997, Reproductive Health and Population became Human Development and Reproductive Health, a subset of the ASSETS Program. William O. Sweeney was retained by the Foundation as Project Specialist for the Population Communications Project when that project was initiated in 1969. Throughout his time with Ford, he travelled extensively assisting developing nations such as China, Egypt, Indonesia, Kenya, Korea, the Philippines, Thailand and Vietnam with the establishment of family planning programs.
(4 Hollinger document boxes)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Separated Materials Note
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Organizational History
The earliest Foundation grants for population research and family planning occurred under the aegis of the Divisions of International Affairs or Overseas Development. The Population Program was officially established in 1963, and became part of the International Division in 1966. Following a Foundation-wide reorganization in 1981, the Population program once again was made independent. In 1992 the Population Program was subsumed into Reproductive Health and Population. Following a second Foundation-wide reorganization in 1997, Reproductive Health and Population became Human Development and Reproductive Health, a subset of the ASSETS Program.
Biographical Note
William O. Sweeney received a J.D. from University of Pennsylvania. Before he joined the Foundation, he worked for Newsweek magazine and the Cursillo Movement of the Roman Catholic Church. The Foundation retained Mr. Sweeney as Project Specialist its Population Communications Project in 1969. Throughout his time with Ford, he helped developing nations to establish family planning programs.
He left the Foundation in 1981. Subsequently Mr. Sweeney was Executive Director of the International Institute of Communications in London and later the International Advertising Association in New York. He died on July 4, 1987 at age 55.
Scope and Content
The Office Files of William O. Sweeney document his work as a project specialist for the Foundation over a span of twenty years. His records document his work in population communications as an advisor to governments in China, Egypt, Indonesia, Kenya, Korea, the Philippines, Thailand, Vietnam and elsewhere. Available in this collection are research reports that Mr. Sweeney prepared throughout his tenure at the Foundation.
One project file of note concerns the proposed establishment of Cycle Communications Associates (CCA), a non-profit agency (1978-1980). Its purpose was to advise non-profits and governments about population communications. Because of concerns that it was not needed, CCA did not receive sustaining Foundation support.
Arrangement note
Collection is arranged in two series.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation’s future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford’s international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee’s report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation’s aspiration‎al goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
- Project Files, 1970-1980; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the files Mr. Sweeney kept of his work on the Foundation’s Population Communications Project and Cycle Communications Associates. The files contain proposals, research, memoranda and correspondence.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - China -- Memoranda Re: UNFPA Communications and Family Planning Project, Project Agreement, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cycle Communications Associates (CCA) -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Incorporation of CCA, Research on Incorporation Process, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cycle Communications Associates (CCA) -- Memoranda Re: Closing Out DAP in Population and Proposal for Establishing CCA, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cycle Communications Associates (CCA) -- Proposal to Establish CCA, Jun 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - DAP Grant Recommendations to Extend Consultancy in Family Planning and Population Communications, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - East-West Communication Institute International Conference on Making Population/Family Planning Research Useful, Honolulu, HI -- Agenda, Discussion Summaries, Papers, Dec 3-7, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Egypt -- Memoranda Re: UNFPA and AID-Sponsored Family Planning Missions, Assessment of AID/Cairo Project, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ford Foundation Population Communications Project -- Evaluation Outline and Comments on Report, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ford Foundation Population Communications Project -- Evaluation Report, May 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Indonesia -- Memoranda Re: Ford Jakarta Field Office Support for National Family Planning Education, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - International Workshop on Communications in Family Planning Programs, Tehran, Iran -- Preliminary Report to the Ford Foundation (1 of 3), Jun 6-18, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - International Workshop on Communications in Family Planning Programs, Tehran, Iran -- Preliminary Report to the Ford Foundation (2 of 3), Jun 6-18, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - International Workshop on Communications in Family Planning Programs, Tehran, Iran -- Preliminary Report to the Ford Foundation (3 of 3), Jun 6-18, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kenya -- Consulting Report on Developing a Family Planning Communications Plan, Proposal to Train Population Communications Personnel, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Korea -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Background on Planned Parenthood Federation of Korea Mothers' Clubs, etc., 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Memoranda -- From Sweeney to Population Office Colleagues Re: Journey from Dacca, Bangladesh to Lomé, Togo, May 19, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Philippines -- Correspondence Re: Workshop to Draft Communications Strategy for Philippine Population Program, Jun 20, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Resources on Development -- Reports, Papers on U.S. Private Voluntary Organizations (PVOs) and Development Education, Videotape as a Development Tool, etc., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Resources on Population Communications -- Papers on Computer and Videotape Communications Technology, Population Education in Developing Countries (1 of 2), 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Resources on Population Communications -- Papers on Computer and Videotape Communications Technology, Population Education in Developing Countries (2 of 2), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Thailand -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Consulting Work with UNFPA and DTCP (Development Training and Communication Planning) (1 of 2), 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Thailand -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Consulting Work with UNFPA and DTCP, Report, Terms of Agreement (2 of 2), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Thailand -- Memoranda Re: Orientation Program for Indochinese Refugees, Background, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - USAID -- Memoranda Re: Grants to Private Voluntary Organizations and Matching Grants Policy, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Vietnam -- Memoranda Re: Meeting with Audiovisual Center for Family Planning, Jun 9, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Reports & Writings, 1968-1977; II
  This series holds Mr. Sweeney’s reports and writings on the subject of population communications. It includes two foreign language reports, one concerning Costa Rica (Spanish language) and the about North Africa (French language).
  Arranged chronologically.
  - "Predictions of Attitude Change for U.S. Roman Catholics", Aug 19, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Family Planning Communications in Nigeria" (consulting report), Mar 1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Suggestions for an Education and Public Information Program for Nutrition, Maternal and Child Health, and Population in Costa Rica" (consulting report), Sep 1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "El Salvador: A Survey of Communications, Information and Education Programs in Family Planning", May 1970 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Guatemala: A Survey of Communications, Information and Education Programs in Family Planning", Jun 1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Kenya: Developing a Family Planning Communications Plan for 1970-1971" (consulting report), Aug 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Central America and Some Caribbean Countries: A Report on Population and Family Planning Information, Education and Communications Programs", Nov 1970 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Jamaica: A Survey of Communications, Information and Education Programs in Family Planning", Nov 1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Ghana: Family Planning Communications: A Program Status Report", May 1971 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Planning Suggestions for Communications Programs", May 1971 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Role of Communications in Family Planning and Population Programs," 1st International Planned Parenthood Federation Workshop on Information and Education, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, Nov 27-Dec 1, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "A Blueprint for Program Planning for Population Communication," Work-Planning Conference, University of Chicago Community and Family Study Center, Dec 16-17, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Communications Program Planning Needs Which Can Be Fulfilled by Library and Information Services," 5th National Conference on Population/Family Planning Library and Information Services, Chapel Hill, NC, May 1972 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "The Role of Communications in Population and Family Planning Programs", May 1972 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "Population and Family Planning: An Approach to Communications as a Program Component", 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Using Commercial Resources in Population Communications Programs", Dec 1972 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Papel Que Desempeñan las Comunicaciones en los Programas de Población y Planificación Familiar," Universidad de Costa Rica Centro de Estudios Sociales y de Población [in Spanish], 1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "A Report on a Visit to Nigeria to Consult on Communications Activities of the Family Planning Council of Nigeria", Mar 1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Communications and the Population Program of Pakistan", Aug 1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Communications and Population in the Philippines: Report of a Visit", Sep 1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Evaluation of the East-West Communications Institute", Sep 1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "A Communication en Afrique," Seminaire sur les Problemes de Population et les Mass Media en Afrique du Nord et au Moyen-Orient, Tunis, Tunisia [in French], Sep 24-29, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Methodology to Support Research Utilization Practitioners," Conference on Making Population/Family Planning Research Useful, East-West Center, Honolulu, HI, Dec 3-7, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "Audiencias para Programas de Información y Educación en Planificación Familiar," Asociación Demográfica Costarricense [in Spanish], 1974 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Population Communications in the Philippines: Report of a Consultant Visit", Jul 1974 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "The Scope of Communications in the Development of Human Resources in the Less Industrialized Countries," Teachers College Record, Dec 1974 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Exchange of Information Between Nations: Help in Solving Population Problems," Bulletin of the American Society for Information Science Vol. 1, No. 8, Mar 1975 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "Population/Family Planning Media Communications in 25 Countries" (monograph), Jun 1977 (Box 4, Folder 14)